<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 22:54:34 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 22:54:34 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Changing the Perception of Women in Tech</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You might have noticed we’re promoting tickets for women in tech. Why’s that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;women-are-underrepresented-in-it&quot;&gt;Women are underrepresented in IT.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tickets first opened up for DevFest, only 21 of the first batch of 300 tickets were registered by women. If that wasn’t bad enough, two cancellations brought that number to a meager 6%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cause of this seems to resonate with the lack of diversity in academia and the workplace in the Netherlands. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vhto.nl/fileadmin/user_upload/images/Cijfers_en_onderzoek/20150605_Gediplomeerden_totaal_htno_per_opleiding_1415.pdf&quot;&gt;According to VHTO (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;, only 3.5% of students studying computer science in 2014 at a professional level are women (30 of 861), with a more startling number of 2.7% (8 of 297) in technical computer science. While slightly better at academic level (7.4% and 6.8%, respectively), one can nevertheless only ponder the reason of this imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While opinions may vary, there are a few different reasons why we and others think that gender diversity is important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversity of thought and essential skills, as women bring different perspectives and knowledge. There is a pool of talent with experience and expertise that has remained almost untapped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the perception of which interests males and females are &lt;em&gt;expected&lt;/em&gt; to have addresses a much larger problem of the mismatch between equal levels of capability and achievement in math and science, and the very different career choices men and women make. Research has shown that parents provide boys and girls with different experiences through the toys they receive and the ways in which praise is given.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging role models to show that computer scientists can put their skills to the greater good can encourage adolescent females to consider it as a field that has a large societal impact. It has been shown that this demographic leans towards biological and medical sciences for this very reason.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Females tend to have higher social intelligence, working better in teams and leading teams than their male colleagues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, better balanced product teams tend to produce products with a competitive edge that are suited to a larger portion of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more detailed explanation about the diversity of experiences, ideas, and social intelligence, and a detailed response to various criticisms of positive discrimination is addressed in &lt;em&gt;A Practical Guide to Gender Diversity for Computer Science Faculty&lt;/em&gt;, in chapter 2, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csee.umbc.edu/courses/undergraduate/CMSC304/Fall2014/PracticalGuideGenderDiversity-Ch2.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why is Gender Diversity Important?&lt;/em&gt; (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-can-we-do-to-help&quot;&gt;What can we do to help?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that a primary cause is perception. A vicious cycle occurs when a gender gap forms, where one group perceives a particular profession as unfavorable. We’ve seen the number of women in STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) on a steady decline since the mid-1980s, and the problem couldn’t become much worse before hitting absolute zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sizable event in technology, we found it in part our responsibility to encourage diversity at GDG DevFest The Netherlands. We’ve taken three distinct approaches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing women an extra opportunity to obtain much wanted tickets to increase female attendance (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/gdg-devfest-the-netherlands-2015-tickets-18232000404?access=women-in-tech&quot;&gt;the promo code is still available!&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arranging for WTM Thessaloniki member Victoria Sinikliyski to address the topic during a heartfelt speech during the afternoon break;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouraging women to speak up and be role models to inspire others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been made possible through the efforts of our committee members and with thanks to the following women communities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Amsterdam-Women-in-Technology/&quot;&gt;Amsterdam Women in Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Geekgirls-Enschede/&quot;&gt;Geekgirls Enschede&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesAMS/&quot;&gt;PyLadies Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Women-Techmakers-Dusseldorf/&quot;&gt;Women Techmakers Düsseldorf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Dusseldorf-Girl-Gone-International/&quot;&gt;Düsseldorf Girl Gone International&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/GirlsCodeEU/&quot;&gt;Girls Code Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-can-you-do-to-help&quot;&gt;What can you do to help?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive feature-image&quot; src=&quot;/img/posts/not_boyfriends_computer.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right;width:35%;margin:0 0 0 16px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please be welcoming of diversity! Encourage friends and colleagues to join in community events. By involving women in developer communities we can begin to change the perception of our industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to women: speak up! Get involved with events like DevFest by submitting an abstract of a topic that you’re passionate about, or volunteer to participate in organizing community events like these. As Chiu-Ki Chan writes in her blog post about Droidcon NYC, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.sqisland.com/2015/08/droidcon-nyc-22-percent-female-speakers.html&quot;&gt;there’s no excuse not to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-to-2016&quot;&gt;On to 2016!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our initiatives from this year are paying off already—female attendance has risen from 6% to 18%—we intend to continue to make strides within our communities to close the gender gap.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 19:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/women-techmakers</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/women-techmakers</guid>
        
        
            
        
            
            <category>en</category>
            
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Call for Papers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;GDG Devfest Netherlands 2015 will be held on Saturday October 10th at the University of Amsterdam. If you want to be part of this great event as a speaker you are invited to submit your Call for Paper as of today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;presenters--who-should-speak-at-the-devfest-conference&quot;&gt;Presenters – who should speak at the DevFest Conference?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developers (freelance and hired)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Companies developing software (apps, tools, frameworks etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research institutions with Google relevant activities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Companies, organisations and individuals using Google technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you belong to one of those groups and if you are a leading expert in Google technologies like Android, Google Cloud, AngularJS, Polymer, Go, The Physical Web, etc. you are cordially invited to submit a talk proposal (or a number of proposals).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;please-submit-your-proposals-herehttpsgooglxztwse&quot;&gt;Please submit your proposals &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/XZtwsE&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadline for submitting your CfP is Friday September 18th, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note: There is no guarantee that a submission will be put onto the conference agenda! The program committee picks the most interesting talk proposals and informs the selected submitters no later than Monday September 21st, 2015.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;any-questions&quot;&gt;Any questions?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email organizers at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#102;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#046;&amp;#110;&amp;#108;&quot;&gt;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#064;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#102;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#046;&amp;#110;&amp;#108;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/call-for-papers</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/call-for-papers</guid>
        
        
            
        
            
            <category>en</category>
            
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
